<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Brief observations upon the vindication of the trinity and incarnation, by the learned Dr. W. Sherlock</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1690</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A77449</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4616B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229472</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99895282</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99895282</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152570</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A77449)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152570)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2305:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Brief observations upon the vindication of the trinity and incarnation, by the learned Dr. W. Sherlock</title>
                  <author>Sherlock, William, 1641?-1707. A vindication of the doctrine of the holy and ever blessed Trinity.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n. ;</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1690]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Drop-head title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Dr. Williams' Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Trinity --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Incarnation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152570:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>BRIEF OBSERVATIONS UPON THE VINDICATION OF THE Trinity and Incarnation, By the Learned Dr. <hi>W. Sherlock.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Notes upon the Creed of <hi>Atha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſius</hi> have been already printed by themſelves, and were received and approved by ſeveral Learned Men, both of <hi>London</hi> and in the Country. Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has thought fit to oppoſe to them a large Book, in which at <hi>Pag.</hi> 142. he ſaith, <hi>My <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking is to vindicate the Athanaſian Creed, and the Doctrine of a Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet in this <hi>Vindication,</hi> he hath given up to his Adverſary, all the ancient Defences of this Creed and of the Trinity, on which his Predeceſſors in this Controverſy, were wont to inſiſt; and has advanced in their room, an Hypotheſis or Explication, never ſo much as named or heard of before. He pretends to ſalve by theſe two words, <hi>Self-conſciouſneſs</hi> and <hi>Mutual-conſciouſneſs,</hi> all the Difficulties of this Great Myſtery; ſo ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently and evidently, that the Notion of a Trinity in Unity, <hi>is now</hi> (He ſaith) <hi>as clear and eaſy, as that of but One God.</hi> But this is too much for any Man to take on his bare word, or without carefully examining what He has ſaid.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Concerning the Divine Subſtance, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Eſſence: for in this Queſtion theſe are Equivalent Terms, both with the Vindicator, and with the Author of the Notes.</item>
               <item>2. How doth he deſcribe the <hi>Three</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; and how is each Perſon <hi>one with it ſelf;</hi> and how are they <hi>diſtinguiſhed</hi> each from other.</item>
               <item>3. How are they <hi>united with one another;</hi> and how do they All make one God.</item>
            </list>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:152570:2"/>
               <head>Firſt; <hi>Concerning the Divine Subſtance, or Eſſence, or Nature.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In his Diſcourſes concerning the Divine Subſtance, or Eſſence; the Vindicator ſeems ſometimes to be a perfect <hi>Hobbiſt;</hi> to deny all Spiritual and Immaterial Subſtance; or that there is any other Subſtance but <hi>Matter,</hi> or Body.</p>
               <p>He ſaith (for example) at <hi>Pag.</hi> 69. <hi>We can frame no Idea of Subſtance, but what we have from Matter.</hi> When we conceive of God as a Subſtance (he ſaith there) <hi>We find it impoſſible to conceive, how there ſhould be Three Divine Perſons, without Three diſtinct Infinite Subſtances.—A Perſon and an Intelligent Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are Reciprocal Terms; and therefore Three diſtinct Perſons, are Three diſtinct Numerical Subſtances; and one Numerical Subſtance, is but one Numerical Perſon.</hi> He ſays, that theſe are all Carnal Reaſonings, which ariſe from our conceiving of God as <hi>a Subſtance;</hi> of which we can have no Idea, but what is <hi>Material.</hi> He concludes in the ſame place, and often elſewhere, <hi>We muſt not ſeek for any other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in God, but Infinite Power, Wiſdom, and Goodneſs.</hi> But as if he had been a little too liberal in that, he ſays at <hi>P.</hi> 72. <hi>Wiſdom and Truth are the true Nature and Eſſence</hi> (or Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) <hi>of God.</hi> He often exhorts his Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, particularly at <hi>P.</hi> 70. <hi>To ſet aſide all theſe Material Images of Eſſence and Subſtance; and to contemplate God as Eternal Truth and Wiſdom, and then the Notion of God is very plain and eaſy.</hi> He adds at <hi>P.</hi> 138. <hi>That which has confounded this Myſtery</hi> (of the Trinity) <hi>has been the vain Endeavour of reducing it to Terms of Art, ſuch as Nature, Eſſence, Subſtance, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, Perſon, Hypoſtaſis, and the like.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He preſumes to ſay at <hi>P.</hi> 139. <hi>The Fathers nicely diſtinguiſhed between Hypoſtaſis or Perſon, and Nature, or Eſſence, or Subſtance; ſaying, that there are Three Perſons, and but one Nature or Eſſence, or Subſtance. But then, when Men curiouſly examined the Signification of theſe words, they found, that upon ſome account or other, they were unapplicable to this Myſtery. For what is the Subſtance and Nature of God? How can Three diſtinct Perſons have but one Numerical Subſtance? What is the diſtinction between Eſſence and Perſonality?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now I ask, Is this to <hi>vindicate the Athanaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Creed,</hi> as the Doctor undertook to do; or to ſlight and overthrow it? The chief buſineſs of the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed, is to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh between the <hi>Subſtance</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> in God, to ſhow that the Perſons are Three, and the Subſtance but One. The Vindicator could not have more effectually given up the Catholick Doctrine to the Note-maker, than by thus frequently denying, there is any real Divine Subſtance at all (which is more than his Adverſary required, and than he will accept) and by ſaying, Men have unduly uſed theſe Terms by their applying them to God. The pretence of the Brief Notes is no other, but what the Vindicator (we have ſeen) often grants: that there is no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Subſtance and Perſon in God; and that therefore Three Divine Perſons and One Divine Subſtance is a ſenſleſs Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction.</p>
               <p>But then 'tis as ſenſleſs to deny the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Subſtance, and to reduce the whole Notion of God to <hi>Wiſdom and Truth;</hi> for theſe are Properties that cannot ſubſiſt, but in ſome Subſtance. Nor do I think, that the Trinitarians will forgo their old Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, by <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Subſtance;</hi> for the Doctor<hi>'s new Wind-mills</hi> of Self-conſciouſneſs and Mutual-conſciouſneſs. They will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly abide by the Nicene and Athanaſian Creeds, which ſuppoſe a Real Divine Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, in which do ſubſiſt Three Divine Perſons. It will be always Hereſy with them, to deny <hi>Homo-ouſios,</hi> or that Chriſt is <hi>of Like and Equal Subſtance</hi> with the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
               <p>I muſt not diſmiſs the Conſideration of the Vindicator's Doctrine, about the Divine Subſtance, without noting, that his Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions to himſelf, are as frequent as his He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terodoxies. For tho he has ſpoken ſo often, ſo expreſly, and ſo much, againſt Subſtance and Perſons in God: yet when <hi>the Metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152570:2"/>Humour</hi> is upon him, he talks of theſe, as of moſt Certain and Real Things. He ſays at <hi>P.</hi> 47. <hi>The Three Perſons are Three Real Subſtantial Beings.</hi> And again, <hi>The Three Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are ſubſtantially diſtinct.</hi> Now this is to ſay, the Three Perſons are Three diſtinct Subſtances: for that is the only poſſible meaning of, <hi>Three Real Subſtantial Beings, ſubſtantially diſtinct.</hi> Thus God at laſt is not only <hi>a Subſtance,</hi> but he is Three Real diſtinct Subſtances. This was the Hereſy of <hi>Valen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus Gentilis,</hi> that the Three Perſons are <hi>Tres Spiritus ſubſtantiali numero differentes.</hi> I wiſh the Vindicator better Succeſs with his Doctrine, than <hi>Valentinus</hi> met at <hi>Geneva</hi> and <hi>Berne.</hi> But the moſt pleaſant of all is, that after the Vindicator had there ſaid, <hi>The Three Divine Perſons are ſubſtantially diſtinct;</hi> he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately ſubjoyns, <hi>tho in one <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndivided Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi> Is it poſſible a Man ſhould give ſo little heed to what he ſays in ſo Great and Nice a Queſtion? He has not <hi>a ſenſible</hi> Friend in the World, that will not tell him, that 'tis as much as to ſay, <hi>The Perſons are Three diſtinct Subſtances, and yet are but one <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndivided Subſtance.</hi> The firſt alone is Hereſy, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperadded to it, makes a groſs Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction. But there are greater Matters, about which I muſt ſpeak with the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>Secondly: <hi>Of the Perſons, their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and their Diſtinction.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>As to the Divine Perſons, and the Unity or Oneneſs of each Perſon with it ſelf, and its Diſtinction from the other two Perſons; he ſays as follows.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pag.</hi> 67.</bibl> A Perſon is ſuch a Being, as has Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Action.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 66.</bibl> They are Three diſtinct and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Minds.—Three Intelligent Beings.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 258.</bibl> They are Three Holy Spirits.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 67.</bibl> Theſe Three Infinite Minds are diſtinguiſhed <hi>juſt as</hi> Three Finite Created Minds are, <hi>by Self-conſciouſneſs.</hi>—Each Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon has a Self-conſciouſneſs of its own, and knows and feels it ſelf, as diſtinct from the other Divine Perſons. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther has a Self-conſciouſneſs of his own, whereby he knows and feels himſelf to be the Father, and not the Son or Holy Ghoſt. The Son feels himſelf to be the Son, and not the Father or Holy Ghoſt. The Holy Ghoſt feels himſelf to be the Holy Ghoſt, and not the Father or Son.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 104.</bibl> The Perſons are <hi>as really</hi> diſtinct, as Three Human Perſons, or Three Men are.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 105.</bibl> Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt are <hi>as really</hi> diſtinct Perſons, as <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 149.</bibl> We muſt believe Three diſtinct Divine Perſons, each of which is God.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 98.</bibl> We muſt allow each Perſon to be <hi>a</hi> God. So alſo at <hi>P.</hi> 47. and elſewhere.</q>
               <p>He not only contends each Perſon is God, and <hi>a</hi> God, but 'tis his Belief (in ſome places of his Vindication) that each Perſon is a moſt conſummate and <hi>abſolutely perfect</hi> God: For he aſcribes to each of them a Perſonal <hi>abſolutely perfect</hi> Wiſdom, Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Juſtice and Power. I ſay, <hi>a Perſonal</hi> perfect Wiſdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beſides the Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> common to them all by their <hi>Mutual-conſciouſneſs.</hi> His words are theſe:</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 81.</bibl> There is no Contradiction, that three Infinite Minds ſhould be <hi>abſolutely perfect,</hi> in Wiſdom, Goodneſs and Power; for theſe are Perfections that may be in more than One.</q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 84, 85.</bibl> The Father has his own <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Wiſdom,</hi> and by Internal Conſciouſneſs, all the Wiſdom of the Son and Holy Ghoſt. The Son has his own Perſonal Wiſdom, and by the ſame Conſciouſneſs, the Wiſdom of the Father and Holy Ghoſt. The Holy Ghoſt has his own Perſonal Wiſdom, and all the Wiſdom of the Father and Son.</q>
               <p>At <hi>P.</hi> 78. He denies there is in God an Infinite Wiſdom, Goodneſs, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but only perfect Wiſdom, Goodneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He acknowledges at <hi>P.</hi> 97. and frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly elſe-where; that if the Divine Perſons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152570:3"/>were <hi>diſtinct and ſeparate</hi> Perſons, they would be Three Gods: but they are, he ſaith, diſtinct, but <hi>not ſeparate</hi> Perſons: Yet he ſaith there, each of theſe Perſons is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ſingly</hi> and <hi>by himſelf,</hi> God, tho not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parately God.</p>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>P.</hi> 48.</bibl> A Finite Spirit's Numerical One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs can be nothing elſe, but every Spirit's Unity with it ſelf, and its diſtinct and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Subſiſtence from all other: Created Spirits. And this <hi>Self-unity</hi> can be nothing elſe but <hi>Self-conſciouſneſs;</hi> or that it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to its own Thoughts, Reaſons, Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which no other Finite created Spirit is conſcious to, but it ſelf.</q>
               <p>Let us put this remarkable Doctrine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Three Divine Perſons into a ſhort Creed, and then make <hi>Brief Notes</hi> upon it.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="creed">
                           <head>Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Creed.</head>
                           <p>I Believe there are Three diſtinct Intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent Infinite Beings, Minds, Spirits, and Perſons; diſtinguiſhed <hi>juſt as</hi> Three Finite Created Minds or Spirits are, <hi>as really</hi> diſtinct as three Men, or as <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John:</hi> Each of them has a <hi>Self-conſciouſneſs,</hi> whereby he knows and feels himſelf, as really diſtinct from the other two Divine Perſons. Alſo each of them has his own <hi>abſolutely perfect</hi> (for there is <hi>no Infinite</hi>) Wiſdom, Goodneſs, and Power: and by <hi>a Mutual-conſciouſneſs,</hi> each Perſon of theſe has the whole Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power and Goodneſs of the two other Perſons. Each Perſon has his own Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Finally, each of theſe Beings, Minds, Spirits, Perſons, is God, nay each of them ſingly <hi>by himſelf</hi> is <hi>a</hi> God.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>This Creed is not only the Vindicator's Senſe, but his very Words, which he has often repeated in his Book. Let us deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berately, and minutely conſider, whether it, be the Faith of Chriſtians, or conſiſtent with Scripture or Reaſon?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I believe there are Three Infinite Spirits, Minds and Beings.</hi> 'Tis the firſt time I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver heard ſo in my Life: That God is <hi>unum ſummum Ens, one Supream Being;</hi> that he is <hi>Animus, Mens, Spiritus,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>a Mind, a Spirit,</hi> is the Voice not only of Scripture, but the agreed Doctrine of all Chriſtians. Let the Vindicator ſhew me, either in Holy Scripture, or in any Catholick Writer, that theſe words are uſed of God in the Plural Number. Do any of them, like this Doctor, call God <hi>Animi Mentes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Minds, Spirits, Beings?</hi> Himſelf is the firſt who has dared thus to ſpeak in expreſs words; and the reaſon is, becauſe he ſaw not what they all ſaw, that three Infinite Minds, Spirits, or Beings, are Three Gods: For if one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite Mind, or Spirit, is One God, Three Infinite Minds, muſt be Three Gods; elſe we cannot diſtinguiſh between One and Three; nor diſcern, that the Definition be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing multiplied, the thing defined is alſo multiplied.</p>
               <p>God, ſaith our Saviour (at <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.24.) is <hi>a</hi> Spirit. No, ſaith the Vindicator (at <hi>p.</hi> 258, and <hi>p.</hi> 66.) God is <hi>Three</hi> Spirits, Minds, or Beings; and to teach the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>is both Hereſy and Non-ſenſe.</hi> Before a Man beſtows ſuch Complements, he ought well to conſider on whom they may reflect: for tho he thinks, that ſuch as <hi>Socinus,</hi> and the Note-maker deſerve not, that common Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity and good Manners be ſhown them; yet he ſhould have had ſome regard for his Saviour.</p>
               <p>Well; but what if Holy Mother <hi>Church</hi> be in the ſame Nonſenſe and Hereſy? Mr. <hi>Savage,</hi> who has alſo written againſt the Brief Notes, will tell him (at <hi>p.</hi> 4. of his Anſwer) that the Lateran Council hath defined, that the Three Divine Perſons are <hi>not Three Beings,</hi> but that <hi>all together they make</hi> Unum ſummum Ens, <hi>One Being.</hi> And I will tell him, that the fourth Council of <hi>Lateran</hi> often repeats it, that God is not <hi>Aliud &amp; Aliud, more Beings or Things;</hi> but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>na quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Res, One Thing or Being.</hi> Mr. <hi>Marlow</hi> in his late Book concerning the Trinity, written
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152570:3"/>(as ſhould ſeem by the Preface) on occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Brief Hiſtory and Brief Notes, deſcribeth God at <hi>p.</hi> 64. <hi>One ſingle Being,</hi> he adds there, <hi>More than one Infinite Being cannot ſubſiſt.</hi> But it were endleſs to cite particular Authorities in this matter: therefore in a word, all Catechiſms, Syſtems, Inſtitutions of Theology, Chriſtian Writers (and even Jews and Mahometans) that have ſpoken of God, do with our Saviour, define him <hi>a</hi> Spirit, one Mind, one Being; never three Spirits, three Minds, or three Beings.</p>
               <p>I dare not ask it of the Vindicator, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he always anſwers according to the preſent Exigence only; but I would ask any other learned and ſenſible Man, What is <hi>the adequate Notion,</hi> or true definition of Three Gods? I make no doubt, every ſuch Perſon would anſwer without any the leaſt Heſitation; three Infinite Spirits, or Minds, or Intelligent Beings, are three Gods: Which is the Vindicator's Definition of one God.</p>
               <p>But to involve himſelf yet more; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves, <hi>Theſe Three Infinite Spirits, Minds, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Perſons, are diſtinguiſh'd juſt as Three Finite Created Minds, or Spirits are; they are as really diſtinct as three Men, or as</hi> Peter, James <hi>and</hi> John. This is Polytheiſm, or <hi>Plurality of Gods</hi> with a witneſs. 'Tis as groſs Polytheiſm, as the Greeks or Romans were ever guilty of. If a Man had asked the Greek Philoſophers, ſuppoſe <hi>Porphyrie</hi> and <hi>Hierocles,</hi> What Conception we ought to have of the three great Objects of Greeian Worſhip, <hi>Jupiter, Neptune,</hi> and <hi>Pluto?</hi> They would have anſwered, as the Vindicator does concerning his Trinity, they are three Divine Beings, Minds, or Spirits, diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>as really,</hi> and <hi>juſt as</hi> three Men, or as <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John.</hi> This was their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytheiſm: not that they believ'd or worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped a falſe God, for that was <hi>ſimple Idolatry,</hi> but that they diſtinguiſh'd the Divinity into three or more Minds, and Beings <hi>as really,</hi> and <hi>juſt as</hi> they diſtinguiſhed three Men, or as <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Vindicator will not be able to give a Rational and Intelligible Account, why it ſhould not as much be Polytheiſm in him to diſtinguiſh <hi>as really,</hi> and <hi>juſt as</hi> the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens did? It will not excuſe him, to ſay, that <hi>Jupiter, Neptune</hi> and <hi>Pluto,</hi> were but ſuppoſed Divine Perſons, but his are really Divine Perſons; for granting ſo much to him for this time, yet to miſtake the Object of their Faith and Worſhip, was only Idolatry; their Polytheiſm conſiſted in diſtinguiſhing the Object of Worſhip, the Divinity, into more Minds or Beings <hi>as really,</hi> and <hi>juſt as</hi> the three Men, <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John</hi> are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh'd.</p>
               <p>Therefore the more Learned Trinitarians have been ſo far from ſaying, the three Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſons are diſtinguiſh'd <hi>juſt as Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> that they never durſt ſay, they are <hi>really</hi> diſtinct, but modally; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more diſtinguiſh'd (they ſay) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween one another, than from their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Eſſence; yet not <hi>really</hi> diſtinct. They conſidered that real Diſtinction makes Alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Diverſity; but the Unity of God does not permit that he ſhould be <hi>Alter, Another,</hi> either from Himſelf, or from any thing that is Himſelf. Since the Eſſence of a thing is <hi>that, by which it is what it is;</hi> whatſoever things are really diſtinct things, muſt alſo be Eſſentially diſtinct; but now the three Divine Perſons having but One Numerical Undivided Eſſence, by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all Trinitarians; therefore they cannot be Eſſentially diſtinct, and therefore not Really, but Modally only. I ſuppoſe therefore the Vindicator's Friends will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail with him, to abate (in his next) ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much of his <hi>as really diſtinct,</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed juſt as</hi> theſe three Men, <hi>Peter, James</hi> and <hi>John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Each of theſe Divine Perſons has a Self-conſciouſneſs, whereby He knows and feels himſelf as diſtinct from the other two Divine Perſons.</hi> This Aſſertion implies what he afterwards adds, that <hi>each of them has his own proper <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will, and Power of Action.</hi> Now I ſay, this is ſo great and clear an Alterity, or Diverſity, that no greater can be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed between any ſort of Intelligent Beings.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152570:4"/>God and his Creatures are not more truly <hi>divers,</hi> than by having each their own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Underſtandings, Wills, and Powers of Action, and by really Being, and Knowing, and Feeling themſelves as diſtinct from one another.</p>
               <p>Intelligent Beings may indeed be farther <hi>differenced</hi> by Eſſential Perfections, or by Degrees of Perfection in the ſame Nature; as Angels are differenced from Men by Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential Perfections, and <hi>Peter</hi> from <hi>John</hi> by Degrees of Human Perfection, and God from his Creatures both by Eſſential Perfections, and by Degrees of thoſe Perfections that are common to him and them: but the meer Alterity or <hi>Diverſity</hi> of Intelligent Beings, or Minds, is no other but what the Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cator has imputed to the Divine Perſons themſelves; namely that each ſuch Being has his own Underſtanding, Will and Power of Action; and both is and knows himſelf as really diſtinct from all others. Perſons or Spirits ſo diſtinct are as really <hi>divers,</hi> or are no more one another, than the Angel <hi>Michael</hi> is the Man <hi>Peter;</hi> or than <hi>Peter</hi> is <hi>Charles,</hi> the Lion in the Tower.</p>
               <p>The Vindicator has diſcourſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all along ſo inconſequently, that I have no hopes he can advert to a Demonſtration, that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires any Attention of Mind: but I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not doubt that others of his Party will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily own, he has very much overſhot him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and that there cannot be ſuch Alterity or Diverſity in God, the moſt ſimple of all Beings. Can there be any thing in God as divers and diſtinct, as <hi>Michael</hi> and <hi>Peter;</hi> nay, as God and his Creatures? They will not ſay it; for 'tis to deny his Simplicity and Unity, and to compound him not only of ſeveral and divers Parts, but of divers and ſeveral Beings, which is too manifeſtly both Heterodox and Impoſſible. Can He be <hi>moſt Simple and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncompounded,</hi> who is made up of three diſtinct Underſtandings, Wills, and Powers of Action; and who is conſtituted of three Beings, or Minds, that know and feel themſelves diſtinct from one another, as diſtinct as <hi>Michael</hi> and <hi>Peter,</hi> and even as God and his Creatures? If ſo, then it may alſo be ſaid, that <hi>God and his Creatures are One moſt Simple <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncompounded Being.</hi> That is the next Paradox the Vindicator has to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend. As for his Mutual-conſciouſneſs, I ſhall demonſtrate in its proper place, that it does not only not heal theſe Breaches, but incu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably widens them, becauſe (I ſhall ſhew) 'tis ſo far from being, or effecting any real Unity and Simplicity, that it implieth and ſuppoſeth an Eſſential Diverſity, and a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate Exiſtence of the Three Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alſo, each of theſe Perſons has his own Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal abſolutely perfect (for there is no Inſinite) Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, and by a Mutual-conſciouſneſs, each of them has all the Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs of the two other Perſons.</hi> This is ſtill ſomewhat a clearer Explication of his Doctrine of Three Gods, than any we have yet had: For ſince each of theſe Spirits, Minds, or Beings has his own Perſonal <hi>abſolutely perfect</hi> Wiſdom, Power and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and that beſides the Conſciouſneſs and Senſation of the <hi>abſolutely perfect</hi> Wiſdom, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the other two; there can be nothing wanting to make each Perſon of them <hi>an abſolutely perfect God.</hi> If there be indeed three <hi>really diſtinct</hi> Spirits, or Perſons, each of which has his own Perſonal abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely perfect Wiſdom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore is unabſolutely perfect God, I doubt whether there be a Man in the World (beſides the Vindicator) who will not acknowledg upon that Suppoſition, that there are three real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſtinct and abſolutely perfect Gods. But as far as he ſeems to be ſunk in his Incogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, I will put to him one Argument.</p>
               <p>'Tis the moſt general and allowed Proof that there is but One God; becauſe one God, or one Infinite Wiſdom, Power, and Goodneſs, is ſufficient, as ſufficient as a thouſand; and there cannot be in God any thing <hi>that is needleſs, uſeleſs, or in vain.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſay, if any one of the Vindicator's Divine Spirits, Minds, Beings, or Perſons, as ſuppoſe <hi>the Father</hi> has <hi>a Perſonal</hi> Infinite (or abſolutely perfect) Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, there can be no need or
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:152570:4"/>occaſion for any other Divine Mind, Spirit, Being, or Perſon; more ſuch Minds were <hi>needleſs, uſeleſs and in vain.</hi> And from hence it clearly follows, that the Unitarians have <hi>the very ſame Evidence,</hi> that there is but one abſolutely perfect Mind, Spirit, Being and Perſon, and but one abſolutely perfect Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Power and Goodneſs, that there is for but One God.</p>
               <p>And whereas Mutual-conſciouſneſs makes <hi>the Beginning, Middle and End</hi> of Dr: <hi>Sher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock</hi>'s Anſwer to the Brief Notes; I would know, of what uſe it can be? What Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection can it be to any of the three Divine Perſons, to be conſcious to the other two, when nothing is gained by it, no Wiſdom, no Power, no Goodneſs? For without ſuch Mutual-conſciouſneſs, each Perſon has <hi>his own Perſonal</hi> abſolutely perfect Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs. The Vindicator has found out a new Attribute in God. Mutual-conſciouſneſs, but will never be able to tell how 'tis any Perfection: Nay, it ſeemeth to be an Imperfection; for to know the ſame things over and over and over by Mutual-conſciouſneſs, which were before fully known by Self-conſciouſneſs, is the ſame in Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, that <hi>Tautology</hi> is in Speech; they are both needleſs Repetitions, and therefore the firſt can no more be in God, than the other in wiſe Men.</p>
               <p>At <hi>p.</hi> 78, and 79. he contends, that 'tis not well ſaid, that God is <hi>an Inſinite</hi> Being, or Spirit, or has <hi>Inſinite</hi> Wiſdom, Juſtice, Power or Goodneſs; becauſe no Being can know what is not to be known; no Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs or Juſtice can go beyond the meaſure, that is, can do exceſſive or unjuſt things; no Power can do impoſſible things. But this is a weak Allegation, tho he propoſes it with his uſual Confidence and Diſdain, to bear him out in this new and impious Hereſy, that the Perfections of God are not Inſirite. For things Unjuſt or Exceſſive are not the Objects of Goodneſs or Juſtice; and 'tis as Ridiculous as 'tis Heretical, to pretend that the Goodneſs and Juſtice of God cannot be Infinite, becauſe He cannot do things that are either Exceſſive or Unjuſt; for this is a chief Reaſon why we aſcribe to God Infinite Goodneſs and Juſtice, even becauſe he can do nothing at all that is Exceſſive or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt. I cannot doubt, but that upon ſecond thoughts, the Vindicator himſelf will diſcern, that it was fillily urged, <hi>the Juſtice of God is not Inſinite, becauſe He cannot do unjuſt things.</hi> As for things <hi>not knowable</hi> and <hi>not poſſible,</hi> they are <hi>Nullities,</hi> and no more the Objects of Wiſdom and Power, or of any other Faculty than things Uunjuſt are of Juſtice; and therefore 'tis as vainly and impertinent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly required, that God ſhould know or do ſuch things by his Infinite Wiſdom and Power, as that He ſhould do unjuſt things by his Infinite Juſtice.</p>
               <p>But I will farther tell this Oppoſer of the Divine Perfections, why it is ſaid the Goodneſs, Juſtice, Wiſdom, and Power of God are each of them Infinite. It is ſo ſaid, becauſe there is in God an inexhauſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Fountain of Goodneſs and Juſtice; that is, he hath an indefectible Propenſity, and an Infinite Inclination of doing always and to all, that which is juſt and good. Alſo the things he knoweth, and which he has and can do, being innumerable and without End, his Wiſdom and Power are alſo Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite, or without End.</p>
               <p>Finally, <hi>He believes each of theſe Beings, Minds, Spirits, Perſons, is God, nay, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of them ſingly by himſelf is a God.</hi> He grants, and ſays, at <hi>p.</hi> 87, and 97. That if the Divine Perſons were <hi>ſeparate</hi> Perſons as well as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Perſons, they were without doubt three Gods. But now are not they ſeparate Perſons, each of which is ſingly and <hi>by himſelf</hi> a Perſon, and God; for what is a ſeparate Perſon, or a ſeparate God, but he who ſingly and <hi>by himſelf</hi> is a Perſon or God? <hi>Single, ſeparate,</hi> and <hi>by himſelf,</hi> are equivalent Terms with all Men but the Vindicator. <hi>By himſelf</hi> is the very Engliſh of the Latin <hi>ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratus,</hi> or ſeparate; therefore in ſaying here, that each Perſon <hi>by himſelf</hi> is God, he hath granted that each Perſon is <hi>ſeparately</hi> God; which is the thing he all along denies and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:152570:5"/>abhors, as a giving up the Queſtion to his Adverſary.</p>
               <p>But he ſays expreſly, each of theſe Perſons is <hi>a</hi> God. None of his Party ever ſaid ſo; they will ſay each of theſe Perſons is God, or is <hi>the</hi> God, becauſe each of them has the Divine Eſſence, which is common to all three; but that each Perſon is <hi>a</hi> God, is without doubt an heretical Form of Speech, and neceſſarily introduces three Gods. For <hi>the</hi> before a Subſtantive, denotes the Unity of the thing ſpoken of, but <hi>a</hi> always ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes more things of the ſame kind. Thus we ſay <hi>the</hi> Sun, <hi>the</hi> Moon, <hi>the</hi> Earth, becauſe there is but one Sun, one Moon, one Earth; and for the ſame reaſon we ſay <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>the</hi> God; but we ſay <hi>a</hi> Spirit, <hi>a</hi> Man, <hi>a</hi> Perſon, becauſe there are more Spirits, Men, and Perſons. Therefore he that ſays, there are three Perſons, each of which is <hi>a</hi> God; or that ſays, the Father is <hi>a</hi> God, or the Son is <hi>a</hi> God, or the Holy Ghoſt is <hi>a</hi> God; ſuch an one (I ſay) profeſſes to believe more Gods. I appeal in this matter to all learned Men, of what Perſwaſion ſoever; and even to all who do but underſtand Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar. But I muſt profeſs my wonder, that ſome Trinitarians in their Explications of their (ſuppoſed) Trinity, are no more care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of avoiding ſuch open <hi>Polytheiſm,</hi> it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Guilt next to Atheiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>Thirdly; <hi>Of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Perſons, and how they make but one God.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Laſt of all; As to the Unity of the three Divine Perſons with one another, and how they all make but one God: He largely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribeth it in his 4th Section, from <hi>Page</hi> 46, to <hi>p.</hi> 86. But the ſum of all is this.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>A Finite Spirit's Unity or Oneneſs with it ſelf, is no other thing but its <hi>Self-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> or that it knows and feels its own Thoughts, Actions, and Paſſions. But if either Finite or Infinite Spirits, Minds, or Perſons are mutually conſcious; that is, are <hi>internally and univerſally conſcious</hi> to one anothers Thoughts, Wills, Actions, and Paſſions, this maketh them to be <hi>truly and properly Numerically One Spirit;</hi> for (<hi>p.</hi> 49.) they are hereby as much one with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as every Spirit is one with himſelf; and (<hi>p.</hi> 56.) they are hereby united to each other, as every Man is to himſelf. To make three Spirits, or Perſons numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally one, it is not enough, that one of them is perfectly conſcious to all the reſt: they muſt all of them be mutually conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous; that is, each of them perfectly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to all the reſt. Thus God is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to all his Creatures, to all their Thoughts, Actions, and Paſſions, as fully conſcious as themſelves are; but they are not hereby made one with him, becauſe they not being conſcious to his Knowledg and Will, there is <hi>not a Mutual-conſciouſneſs</hi> between God and them. The Mutual-conſciouſneſs of the three Divine Perſons, is the <hi>Perichóreſis</hi> and <hi>Circuminceſſion</hi> men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by the Fathers and the Schools. For <hi>Perichóreſis,</hi> or that the Father is in the Son and Spirit, and the Son in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Spirit, and the Spirit in the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son, is nothing elſe but their uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Mutual-conſciouſneſs. We ought not to entertain a groſs material Idea of the <hi>Perichóreſis,</hi> as if the three diſtinct Divine Perſons were in one another by a mutual Contract of Parts, for they have no Parts; <hi>the only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Perichóreſis</hi> of Minds and Spirits is, that they are conſcious each to others Thoughts and Wills, as perfectly and inwardly as to their own. And thus alſo it is, that the three Divine Perſons are one God; they are one God, and in one another <hi>by perfect Mutual-conſciouſneſs.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Vindicator often ſays, that this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the Trinity, maketh a Trinity in Unity as eaſy and intelligible as the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of One God, or but one who is God. But being aware that 'tis not enough that an Explication be intelligible, if it be not alſo the true Explication; therefore he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to prove this Mutual-conſciouſneſs of the Father, Son, and Spirit, from <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. &amp; 10.15, 30 38. &amp; 16.14, 15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10, 11.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:152570:5"/>Then for the Fathers, tho they do not once name Mutual-conſciouſneſs, yet he thinketh they meant it. He alledges a few Paſſages out of <hi>Gregory Nyſſen</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> who are all the Fathers he quotes, and his Citations are not only not to his purpoſe, but ſome of them clearly overthrow it. I ſhall ſhew him the reſpect, to conſider what he hath ſaid.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Whereas he ſaith, that Mutual-conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs maketh the three Divine Spirits, to be <hi>as truly and properly numerically one;</hi> and <hi>as much one, as each Spirit and every Man is one with himſelf.</hi> If this were indeed true, it would as much over-do what the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor expects from it, as he thinketh all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Explications are ſhort of their Deſign. For the Unitarians deſire no more, than that it be owned, God is as truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly numerically one, <hi>as every Spirit and Man is one with himſelf;</hi> for every Spirit and Man is ſo one with himſelf, as to be <hi>but one Perſon.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had the Vindicator no way to defend the Athanaſian Creed, but by running into He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy? could he make out the Unity of the Trinity, no other way but (as the Creed ſpeaks) <hi>by confounding the Perſons,</hi> or by making them but one Perſon? I challenge him, or any other for him, to avoid this Conſequence of his Doctrine. He ſaith in above twenty places, this Mutual-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs maketh the three Divine Spirits and Perſons as much one with one another, as any Spirit or Man is one with himſelf; then ſay I, they are but one Perſon; for that is the Oneneſs or Unity (the only Unity) of every Spirit or Man with himſelf. No Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit or Man has any other but a Perſonal Unity with himſelf.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Mutual-conſciouſneſs cannot be a good Explication of the (pretended) Trinity, becauſe it will equally ſalve the moſt abſurd Doctrine of the Tranſubſtantiation. For as, according to the Vindicator's Doctrine, <hi>the Godhead,</hi> or the One true God, is numerically One, tho there are three Infinite Perſons, each of which is God, and <hi>a</hi> God; becauſe theſe three Perſons are mutually conſcious to, or have an inward Senſation of one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: So will a Papiſt ſay, there is but one <hi>Body-head,</hi> or but one Numerical Body of Chriſt; but in the Unity of this <hi>Body-head</hi> or Body, there is firſt the Original Body of Chriſt, and then abundance of Sacred <hi>Hoſts</hi> in divers places, each of which is a true Body of Chriſt, and is by Mutual Senſation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs (for there is no Senſation without Conſciouſneſs) numerically one Body with the Original Body in Heaven. 'Tis true, the Body in Heaven is the Source and Fountain of the reſt, as the Father is of the other Divine Perſons, but they are all <hi>ſubſtantially and numeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cally</hi> one Body, by Mutual-conſciouſneſs or Senſation. And this mutual inward Senſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Conſciouſneſs they muſt needs have, becauſe they are all of them <hi>Perſonally w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ited</hi> to one Infinite Spirit or Perſon, who (as all Trinitarians ſay) is <hi>Whole and All</hi> every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where preſent, <hi>Totus in toto, &amp; totus in qualibet parte.</hi> By this Explication or <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> all Mr. <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s Demonſtrations againſt the Tranſubſtantiation, are made to vaniſh into Smoke. All his Objections from the nature of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Extenſion</hi> are nothing; they are all ſalved by Mutual-conſciouſneſs of <hi>the Hoſts</hi> with the Body in Heaven; for Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> has aſſured us, that Mutual-conſciouſneſs or Senſation, doth make <hi>an Eſſential, Subſtantial and Numerical <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> or Oneneſs between any number of Perſons or Things. The Reaſon holds for <hi>Things</hi> as well as <hi>Perſons,</hi> and for a thouſand as well as for three.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If, as the Vindicator often ſays, Mutual-conſciouſneſs is <hi>the only <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Spirits or Minds,</hi> ſuch a Mutual-conſciouſneſs by which they are univerſally, or wholly, or pefectly conſcious to each other; this would as much prejudice the Incarnation, or Hypoſtatical Union, as the Vindicator hopes it will help the Doctrine of the Trinity. The Vindicator con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes at <hi>p.</hi> 269, and 270, that the Human Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Reaſonable Soul of Chriſt, is not uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally, or wholly conſcious to the Divine Perſon of the Son; yet he ſays in perhaps forty places, that a Mutual-conſciouſneſs to all one anothers Thoughts and Wills and Actions is neceſſary to make an Union of Minds or Spirits. I ſay, it follows from theſe
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152570:6"/>Premiſes, that the Reaſonable Soul or Spirit of the Lord Chriſt is not united to the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Perſon of the Son. If univerſal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs is <hi>the only poſſible <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> of Spirits, 'tis impoſſible there ſhould be an Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or an Hypoſtatical or Perſonal Union of the Divine and Human Spirits in Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The Vindicator ſeems to have been, in ſome meaſure, aware of this Objection. For in the Concluſion of his Book, when he comes to the Doctrine of the Incarnation, or Hypoſtatical Union, he ſays,
<q>Where diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Natures are united into one Perſon, this univerſal Conſciouſneſs is ſeated only in the Superior Nature; and in the Infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior, only ſo far as the Nature is capable, and as the Perſonal Union requires.</q> But I will forgive the Vindicator, if he can ſo eſcape from me.</p>
               <p>Firſt; If, as he ſays, a partial Conſciouſneſs in the Inferior Nature be ſufficient to effect an Hypoſtatical or Perſonal Union, it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that all pious Men are hypoſtatically or perſonally united to the Holy Ghoſt. For the Holy Spirit is univerſally conſcious to all their Thoughts and Actions, and they are partially conſcious to his Suggeſtions and Motions, and that by ſuch <hi>an Internal Senſation</hi> as they are to their own Thoughts and Inclinations. They cannot diſcern one from the other.</p>
               <p>Secondly; If <hi>a Partial Conſciouſneſs</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two or more Spirits, where but one of them is univerſally conſcious to the reſt, will make them numerically one Perſon, or (what is the ſame thing) will effect an Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatical or Perſonal Union; then certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly where two or more Spirits are <hi>univerſally conſcious</hi> to one another, it muſt much more make them numerically one Perſon, or effect an Hypoſtatical or Perſonal Union. From whence it will follow, that the three Divine Perſons being univerſally conſcious to one another, are numerically one Perſon, and are hypoſtatically and perſonally united. But this every one knows is Hereſy, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Athanaſian Creed, which forbids us <hi>to confound the Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly; But the truth is, a Partial Mutual-conſciouſneſs in one of the Spirits (tho the other be univerſally conſcious) is not ſufficient to make a Perſonal Union, or to make two or more Perſons to be nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merically one Perſon. The Reaſon is this, ſince univerſal Mutual-conſciouſneſs is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid (by the Vindicator) to make more Spirits to be numerically one, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>in every one of them</hi> it amounts to as much as, and is equivalent to the Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs or Self-unity of each Spirit with it ſelf; for it makes more Spirits as conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to one another (and therefore as nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rically one) as every Spirit is to it ſelf: from hence it neceſſarily follows, that a Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Conſciouſneſs which is not univerſal in both Spirits, cannot effect a Perſonal Union, or make them numerically one Perſon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe 'tis undeniable that one of theſe Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits (the inferior Nature or Spirit) has not ſuch a Mutual-conſciouſneſs with the other Spirit, as is equal to its own Self-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which makes it Self-unity.</p>
               <p>Hitherto I have ſo argued, as to ſuppoſe, with the Vindicator, that ſuch a Mutual-conſciouſneſs as he has deſcribed when 'tis univerſal, may have the effect he ſuppoſeth; that is, may effect a Numerical Oneneſs or Unity, and have only ſhewn, that however it has ſeveral ſuch Heretical Conſequences, that it muſt not be admitted by him or any other. For we have ſeen it maketh the three Divine Perſons to be but one Perſon, becauſe (he ſaith) it makes them as much one, as each Spirit, Perſon, or Man is one with himſelf. Alſo this <hi>Hypotheſis</hi> will do as much Service to the Tranſubſtantiation, as to the Trinity; for it will make as Subſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial and Numerical an Unity between the <hi>Hoſts</hi> and the Body in Heaven, as between the three Divine Spirits. Farther, it deſtroys the Hypoſtatical Union; for 'tis plain that a Partial Conſciouſneſs between the Human and Divine Spirits in the Lord Chriſt, cannot make a Perſonal Union, or make them nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merically one Perſon, becauſe in his Human Spirit 'tis not equal to that Self-conſciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which the Vindicator affirms to be the Self-unity of every Intelligent Being. But now I ſhall prove, that,</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:152570:6"/>
               <p n="4">4. Mutual Conſciouſneſs, notwithſtanding the Vindicator's confident Affirmation, and frequent Repetition of it, doth not indeed make the three Divine Perſons to be nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merially one, or ſo one, as each Spirit and every Man is one with himſelf; nay, it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is nor effecteth any real Unity at all. For tho he is careful to ſuppoſe, that the three Perſons are mutually conſcious <hi>by an internal Senſation,</hi> and that they are conſcious <hi>to all</hi> the Thoughts, Wills and Actions of one another, as each Perſon of them, and as every Man is internally conſcious to all his own Thoughts and Action, all which he thinketh muſt make them numerically one Spirit and one God; becauſe (in his Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion) it amounts to as much as, and is equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent to, that Self-conſciouſneſs which is (he ſaith) the Self-unity of each Spirit, and every Man with himſelf. Tho (I ſay) he is careful to ſuppoſe thus much, yet I ſhall mind him of a thing which will ruin his whole <hi>Hypotheſis;</hi> even this, that the three Divine Spirits or Perſons, tho they are uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally and internally conſcious to one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet becauſe they are not <hi>in the ſame manner</hi> conſcious to one anothers Thoughts and Actions, as each Spirit of them and each Man is conſcious to his own Thoughts and Actions; therefore the Mutual-conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs which he ſuppoſes they have, cannot make them numerically one Spirit, or one God. None of them is conſcious to the Thoughts and Actions of the other two <hi>as his own,</hi> but as riſing <hi>in</hi> and <hi>from</hi> the other Perſons; but each of theſe Spirits and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Man is conſcious to his own Thoughts and Actions, as ariſing <hi>in</hi> and <hi>from</hi> himſelf, from his own Perſonal Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Action.</p>
               <p>Let me hear the Vindicator ſay, that the Son (for Example) knows and feels the Thoughts and Actions of the Father and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, not as the Thoughts and Actions of the Father and Spirit, but <hi>as his own Perſonal Thoaghts and Actions,</hi> or as originated in his own Perſon; and I will allow that ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs doth look ſomewhat like a nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Oneneſs or Unity. But I will demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate to him, that ſo to ſay, is both Hereſy and a Contradiction.</p>
               <p>It is Heretical, becauſe then the Father's Perſonal Action of <hi>Generation</hi> would be known and felt by the Son, <hi>as the Action of the Son;</hi> that is, the Son would know and feel that he begets himſelf. Alſo <hi>the mutual Love</hi> of the Father, and of the Image, or Son, whereby (as this Athanaſian Doctor feigns) the Holy Spirit proceeds from them, would be known and felt by the Holy Spirit, as his own Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Action, not as the Action of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Son. Both which are Heretical when affirmed by any.</p>
               <p>But beſides, that 'tis Hereſy, 'tis alſo a Contradiction: 'Tis juſt as much a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, as to ſay, that the Perſon and Perſonal Underſtanding of the Son, is the Perſon and Perſonal Underſtanding of the Father. If we confound the Perſons and Perſonal Thoughts and Actions of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Spirit, we confound alſo their Perſonal Underſtandings, Wills, and Powers of Action. If each Perſon of them has his Perſonal Underſtanding, Will, and Power of Action, he has alſo his Perſonal Thoughts and Actions; and conſequently, the Son cannot feel the Thoughts and Actions of the Father, <hi>as his own</hi> Perſonal Thoughts and Actions, but as the Thoughts and Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Father. But if ſo, all Men muſt grant, that ſuch Mutual-conſciouſneſs of the three Divine Perſons, neither is nor effecteth a Numerical Unity, or any Unity at all. It cannot, I ſay, make them one Spirit, or One God, but leaves them as much three as other <hi>ſeparate</hi> Spirits or Beings are. For 'tis ſuch a Conſciouſneſs as may be, and actually is, between the moſt oppoſite contrary and ſeparate Natures and Spirits. For all Men are after this manner conſcious both to the Holy Spirit and to the Tempter. We are conſcious to the Suggeſtions and Motions of the firſt, and to the Temptations of the other, <hi>by an internal Conſciouſneſs;</hi> nay by ſuch a perfect intimate Conſciouſneſs, that we do not always diſcern them from our own Perſonal Thoughts, or the Motions and Actings of our own Spirits; which is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152570:7"/>
                  <hi>a cloſer Conſciouſneſs</hi> than the Vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor has ſuppoſed, or dares ſuppoſe between the three Divine Perſons; and yet it leaves us ſeparate Beings and Spirits, both from the Holy Spirit, and from the Tempter.</p>
               <p n="5">5. If there were indeed ſuch a thing as the Vindicator's mutual Conſciouſneſs, I do affirm, it would be ſo far from being, or from effecting a numerical Unity or Oneneſs, that it would be the very thing which would moſt of all prove the three (pretended) Divine Perſons are numerically three Spirits and three Gods. For ſince, according to the Vindicator's Deſcriptions, each of theſe Spirits or Perſons has his own Perſonal Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, Will and Power of Action, and his own Perſonal abſolutely perfect Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs; three ſuch Perſons are ſo far from being one Spirit or one God, by Conſciouſneſs to each other Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs, that the more ſuch Perſons are mutually conſcious, ſo much the more their <hi>ſeparate</hi> Exiſtence and Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity is proved. For the more that any of theſe Spirits knows and feels of Thoughts and Actions ariſing in the other Spirits or Perſons, and to which he is only conſcious, but is not the Perſonal Fountain of them; the more, and more certainly, he muſt needs know and feel, that himſelf has a divers and ſeparate Exiſtence from them, and therefore (being an Infinite Perſon or Spirit) is a divers and ſeparate God.</p>
               <p>I challenge the Vindicator to tell me any other poſſible way for three Divine Perſons to be aſſured of their ſeparate Exiſtence and Divinity; that is, that they are three Gods, but by Mutual-conſciouſneſs, or by knowing and feeling (as he ſpeaks) the Thoughts and Actions of one another, <hi>not as their own,</hi> but as the Thoughts and Actions of other Divine Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. How ſhould the Father, for example, know He is a ſeparate Spirit and God from the Son, but by knowing and feeling the Actions of the Son, not as his (the Fathers) Actions, but as the Actions and Thoughts of another Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and Infinite Perſon? It was therefore a great Incogitance in the Vindicator, to urge the (pretended) Mutual-conſciouſneſs of the three (pretended) Divine Perſons, as their numerical Unity or Oneneſs, when it de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrates them to be numerically three ſeparate and divers Beings, Spirits and Gods.</p>
               <p>Had the Vindicator ſaid, there are three Infinite Spirits, who are mutually conſcious, THEREFORE there are three Gods; all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind would have allowed his Conſequence, as certain and ſelf-evident from that Propoſition. But to ſay there are three Infinite Spirits, conſcious to one another, THEREFORE there is but one God; this all Men of Senſe will laugh at, as <hi>a palpable</hi> Falſhood. 'Tis a Contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Terms, to tell us of <hi>One only God mutually conſcious;</hi> for in plainer Engliſh 'tis to ſay, <hi>One only God conſcious to, or with other Gods.</hi> Or, <hi>One only God conſcious to more Gods.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. But the great Matter is ſtill behind, that after all, our Bleſſed Saviour himſelf has declared, that there is not this Mutual-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciouſneſs between the (ſuppoſed) Divine Perſons, which the Vindicator has made to be the Subſtance of his Anſwer to the Brief Notes, and the Brief Hiſtory. <hi>Of that day and hour</hi> (the day and hour of the laſt Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) <hi>none knoweth, no not the Angels which are in Heaven, nor the Son, but the Father only; Mark</hi> 13.32. <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.36. Here it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly denied, that the Son knows the time of the laſt Judgment, and as clearly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timated that the Father, and <hi>the Father only</hi> (therefore not the Holy Ghoſt, if we take the Holy Ghoſt for a particular Perſon) knows that time. Therefore, ſay I, the Son and Holy Ghoſt are not conſcious to all the Knowledg, Will and Thoughts of the Father, and conſequently are not Gods, or God.</p>
               <p>To avoid this Argument, the Vindicator and his Party anſwer, that Chriſt in that Text ſpeaks of himſelf, only as he is a Man, not as he is God, or <hi>a</hi> God. Well, but how ſhall we ſalve the Honour of the Holy Ghoſt, for 'tis there alſo ſaid, that <hi>the Father only</hi> knoweth that day and hour? Why, for that, the word <hi>Father</hi> here does not ſignify <hi>the Father only,</hi> but includes the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt. But when mention is made of the <hi>Father</hi> and the <hi>Son</hi> in the ſame Period, and they are oppoſed to each other, 'tis
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152570:7"/>much that neither the Son ſhould ſignify the Son, (for the Human Nature, or Chriſt <hi>as Man,</hi> according to the Trinitarians, is not the Son) nor the Father ſignify the Father, but the Father and two other Perſons. If this be not to form the Scriptures to our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conceived Opinions, and not our Opinions by the Scriptures; let the Vindicator him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf tell me, what is? Should a Socinian di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtort the known ſenſe and uſe of Words at this rate, what Out-cries ſhould we have againſt them!</p>
               <p>Nor was it our Saviour's manner to anſwer after this equivocal deluſory faſhion: But when the Diſciples were more inquiſitive than he liked of, he was not wont to ſhift off the matter by an Equivocation, but plainly to tell them, They asked after what 'twas not permitted to them to know. <hi>Wilt thou at this time reſtore the Kingdom to Iſrael?</hi> ſay the Diſciples at <hi>Acts</hi> 1.6, 7. <hi>'Tis not for you to know,</hi> ſaith our Saviour. How unlike is this direct ſincere Anſwer to that which the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitarians have made for him about the Day of Judgment? For their Anſwer runs thus;
<q>As to the day and hour of Judgment, of which you enquire, none knoweth it, not the Angels, not the Son himſelf, but my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther only. But when I ſay the Son, that is, <hi>I my ſelf</hi> know it not, I mean <hi>(ſaith he to himſelf)</hi> according to my Human Nature, which indeed is not the Son; and when I ſay, only my Father knoweth it, I mean <hi>(ſaith he again to himſelf)</hi> only my Father <hi>and my ſelf,</hi> and the Holy Ghoſt.</q> This is ſuch <hi>an over-grown Equivocation,</hi> and Mental Reſervation, as in our Town would paſs for a groſs Lie: but that the Vindicator and his Party have aſſured us, that our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſpake thus. But I do not think any ſenſible and honeſt Man will believe 'em, if he conſiders it twice.</p>
               <p>'Tis thus alſo that they have dealt with God himſelf, ſpeaking in the firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but Me,</hi> ſaith God in the words of the firſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment. And to render this his Soveraign Revelation and Will the more awful and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by us, he delivered it in Thunders that ſhook the Heavens and the Earth. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, and tho every one knows, that the Stile of Laws is plain and ſimple, and the words to be underſtood in a popular familiar Senſe, becauſe they are delivered to the meaneſt as well as the higheſt Capacities; yet have thoſe who call themſelves the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and the Catholick Party eluded this Revelation and Law, to which all the reſt refer, and on which they depend, and have made room for <hi>other Gods beſides him. Thou ſhalt have no other Gods beſides Me;</hi> that is, (ſay they) Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> no other Gods, but God the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt: Thou ſhalt have no other Gods, but three Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Almighty, All-knowing Perſons; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of one is the Father, another his Son, and the third an holy Spirit diſtinct from both.</p>
               <p>I perſwade my ſelf that no Man can think that ſo much as one Perſon of the ſix hundred thouſand <hi>Iſraelites</hi> who aſſembled to hear God ſpeak, did (or poſſibly could) underſtand that to be his meaning; but on the contrary, when they heard, <hi>Thou ſhalt have no other Gods but Me,</hi> they did, and their Poſterity to this day do, underſtand it no otherways but thus, <hi>Thou ſhalt never know or own more than one Divine Perſon, even Me who now ſpeak to thee.</hi> When Points of Faith are turned into Laws, we ought to be careful how we elude their plain and obvious Senſe <hi>by Subtilties;</hi> for ſuch things will not excuſe the Breach of Laws, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the firſt and chief Law, the ground of the reſt, to which they all refer as their chief Deſign. Rather we ſhould interpret all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther dubious and diſputable Scripture-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions by ſuch ſolemn Principal and Chief Revelations and Laws. The Vindicator, 'tis ſaid, is writing a Book to prove, that there are more Perſons (the Son and Spirit) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Eternal <hi>God and Father of our Lord Chriſt,</hi> who are Gods, or God, that is, he is writing a Book againſt the firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. And I confeſs, that as his Party have ordered the vulgar Editions and Tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Holy Bible, it will be no hard matter to alledg ſome very plauſible Texts to ſuch as know not the Deceits that have
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152570:8"/>been uſed, to make ſome Texts of Scripture contradict others. But I challenge him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-hand, to produce but one ſuch Proof or Text for his purpoſe, as is not of ſuch <hi>ſuſpected Credit</hi> and Authority in the Originals, that no prudent Man would build any thing on it, much leſs oppoſe it to the firſt Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or is ſo <hi>manifeſtly ſaulty in the Engliſh Tranſlation,</hi> that ſome of the moſt Learned of his own Party do reject it as no Proof; or finally, is not only <hi>not to his purpoſe,</hi> but proves what the Unitarians contend for, the Unity of God, or that <hi>God is One.</hi> But this was a Digreſſion; I left off at our Saviour's words, <hi>Of that day and hour</hi> (the day and hour of the laſt Judgment) <hi>none knoweth but my Father only,</hi> which I hope were ſufficiently vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the Perverſions of Dr. <hi>Sherlock,</hi> and others.</p>
               <p>But let our Saviour ſay what he will, and as expreſly as he will, the Doctor will prove againſt him, that there is this perfect Mutual-conſciouſneſs between Him, the Holy Spirit, and the Father.</p>
               <p>His firſt Objection is from <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.18. <hi>The only Begotten Son which is in the Boſom of the Father, hath declared him.</hi> To be <hi>in the Boſom of another,</hi> ſignifies, ſays the Vindicator, to be conſcious to that Perſon's Mind, and moſt intimate Secrets; therefore the Son is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcious to the Father. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But why did not the Vindicator produce ſome Texts to confirm this Interpretation? The truth is, the Scripture-Senſe of this Phraſe, <hi>To be in the Boſom of another,</hi> is this, <hi>to be moſt dear</hi> to that Perſon, as is clear from <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.54, 56. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.3. So the Senſe of the objected Text is only this, The only Begotten Son, who is moſt dear to the Father, hath declared him, <hi>i. e.</hi> hath made known his Will and Commands in the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>He objects, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.15. <hi>As the Father knoweth me, ſo know I the Father. Anſw.</hi> If the Vindicator had look'd into the Critical Commentators of his own Party, he would have ſeen, that <hi>to know</hi> in this Text is <hi>to love.</hi> But allowing him his Senſe of the words; I anſwer, as much is propheſied of all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in Goſpel-times, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. <hi>They ſhall all know me, from the greateſt to the leaſt of them.</hi> Nor does <hi>[as]</hi> here note Equality of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge in the Son, but Likeneſs only; as at <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.48. <hi>Be ye perfect, even as your Father which is in Heaven, is perfect.</hi> Therefore the Senſe is, the Father knoweth me, and I alſo know the Father (not by Natural or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genit Conſciouſneſs, but) by his Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. See <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1.</p>
               <p>Joh. 10.30. <hi>I and the Father are One.</hi> This Oneneſs or In-being, ſaith the Vindicator, is a Mutual-conſciouſneſs and inward Senſation of each other. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But our Saviour ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains this Oneneſs, to be ſuch an Unity or Oneneſs as is (or ſhould be) among all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians; which is not by Mutual-conſciouſneſs or inward Senſation, but Mutual and Inward Love of one another. <hi>John</hi> 17.11. <hi>Father, —keep thoſe whom thou haſt given me, that they may be One as we are.</hi> Ver. 22. <hi>That they may be One, even as we are One.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, he urgeth <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.38. <hi>The Father is in me, and I in him.</hi> The Vindicator in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth much on this, as a clear Indication of an inward Conſciouſneſs between the Father and Son. <hi>Anſw.</hi> But here again our Saviour has otherways explain'd himſelf, namely thus, that he means ſuch an In-being as is between all Chriſtians and the Father; an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being by Love, and the Gift of the Spirit, on the part of the Father, and on our part, by Love, and Obedience, and Profeſſion of the Truth: <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.21. <hi>That they all may be One, as thou Father art in me, and I in thee, that they may be One in us.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.24. <hi>He that keepeth his</hi> (God's) <hi>Commandments, dwelleth in Him, and he in him.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.13. <hi>Hereby we know we dwell in him, and he in us, becauſe he hath given us of his Spirit.</hi> Ver. 15. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall confeſs, that Jeſus is the Son of God, God dwelleth in him, and he in God.</hi> Ver. 16. <hi>He that dwelleth in Love, dwelleth in God, and God in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Joh. 16.15. <hi>All things that the Father hath are mine. Anſw.</hi> See what hath been ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factorily ſaid to this, in the Brief-Hiſtory, <hi>pag.</hi> 103.</p>
               <p>1 Cor. 2.10, 11. <hi>The Spirit ſearcheth all things, yea the deep things of God. For what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152570:8"/>Man knoweth the things of a Man, but the Spirit of a Man, which is in him? even ſo the things of God knoweth no Man, but the Spirit of God. Anſw.</hi> The Emphaſis lies here; that the Spirit knows the things of God, <hi>even as</hi> the Spirit of a Man knows the things of a Man. Now adinitting, that the Holy Ghoſt or Spirit were a Perſon, as many Unitarians (particularly the <hi>Bidellians</hi> and <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi>) believe he is, chief of the holy Spirits or Angels, and called <hi>the Spirit</hi> by way of Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and <hi>the Holy Spirit,</hi> to diſcriminate him from Satan, who is chief of the Wicked and Apoſtate Spirits or Angels. Admitting, I ſay, that the Holy Spirit is a Perſon, yet what hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders that he may <hi>know the things of God,</hi> that is (appears by Ver. 9.) <hi>the things that God has pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them that love him,</hi> as fully and perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as the Spirit of a Man knoweth the Deſigns and Counſels of a Man towards other Men? Cannot God as fully reveal thoſe <hi>things of God</hi> to this holy and ſuper-eminent Spirit, as any Man knows his own Will and Deſigns of Good towards others? and is it not thus, that our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour alſo is ſaid to know the things of God? <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.1.</p>
               <p>If it be demanded, If this be all, Why is this Spirit called <hi>the Spirit of God?</hi> I hope the Vindicator knows, that 'tis the manner of the Hebrew Tongue to name things great in their kind, by the name of God. He may alſo be called <hi>the Spirit of God,</hi> as Prophets are in Scripture called <hi>the Men of God,</hi> becauſe both one and the other <hi>are ſent by God.</hi> And this Spirit is ſo much the Chief of all other Spirits, that are God's Meſſengers; that he is therefore ſometimes called by way of Eminence and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellence, <hi>the</hi> Spirit of God. So an <hi>Arian</hi> or <hi>Bidellian</hi> Unitarian would anſwer to the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection from this Text. How a <hi>Socinian</hi> Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian would anſwer, may be ſeen in the Brief Hiſtory, from <hi>p.</hi> 98, to <hi>p.</hi> 102.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>The <hi>CONCLUSION.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THus I have conſider'd Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s new Explication of the Doctrines of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and Incarnation by Self-conſciouſneſs and Mutual conſciouſneſs, and therein the ſubſtance and force of his Book, which he has ſo vainly and untruly called <hi>a Vindication</hi> of thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines. His Book can deſerve that Title in no other ſenſe, but as 'tis a ſupercilious, diſdainful, and peeviſh Anſwer. But for that, the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians know very well, that when Learned Men rage in ſuch a manner, that they have neither Humanity nor good Manners left, <hi>'tis becauſe they find themſelves pinch'd:</hi> they know too, that <hi>Omnis Renegada eſt Ordinis ſui Perſecutor.</hi> Thoſe who have hitherto ſaid (who are all that have read his Books) there is nothing conſiderable in Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Books, but what he either bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from the <hi>Socinians,</hi> or build upon their Foundation; ſuch will wonder he would ſhew no better Reaſons why he hath ſhifted ſides. He promiſed at <hi>P.</hi> 21. <hi>to examine the Brief Notes Paragraph by Paragraph, that the Author might not complain of unſair <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage:</hi> But at <hi>p.</hi> 256, before he was got half thorough the Notes, he pretends to grow <hi>weary of the Note-maker's long Harangues</hi> (tho the whole Notes are leſs than a Sheet of Paper) and ſo gives his Reader only ſo much of the Brief Notes as he fancied he could deal withal. Therefore the Author of the Notes will ſay, this was not only unfair, but (after a Promiſe) <hi>falſe <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſage:</hi> Others ſay, the Doctor grew ſelf-conſcious, ſenſible of his Inability, and therefore durſt not truſt his Reader with thoſe dangerous Notes, and his crude Anſwer to them. But where he pretended to anſwer, he ſhould not have ſuppreſſed ſo many Periods, nor omitted to take notice of <hi>the Reaſon</hi> uſed, ſuppoſing it was enough if he oppoſed <hi>the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi> Leaſt of all ſhould an Anſwerer of his ſtanding and Reputation in Polemic Squabble, have quietly paſt by ſome whole Paragraphs, the moſt material in the Notes; or only caſt a bald ſqueez'd Jeſt at 'em.</p>
               <p>As to the ſlight <hi>Querks</hi> which he ſometimes oppoſes to the <hi>Arguments</hi> in the Notes and Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, there is an Anſwer preparing, and almoſt finiſh'd, to every thing in his Book, to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd, unleſs in his next he is content to own <hi>he deſires it not.</hi> For as to the Unitarians them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, they are upon ſeveral accounts not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152570:9"/>to publiſh a farther Anſwer. Firſt, They foreſee, that the Vindication is not a Book, by which the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or any other Party of the Trinitarians, will abide; they look for another kind of Anſwer, and therefore reſerve their Defences to a time and occaſion that may more require them. Another Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, they dare truſt the Hiſtory and Notes with the Doctor's Anſwer, tho he durſt not truſt his Anſwer with the Notes; only they deſire the Reader to read the Notes and Hiſtory as they are publiſh'd by them, in entire Diſcourſes, not as they are mangled, and cut into Thongs by the Vindicator. They are confident, that no diſcerning Man who ſhall read Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s Vindication, and afterwards read again the Notes or Hiſtory, as they are publiſh'd by the Unitarians, but will ſind himſelf as much trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled to untie <hi>the Gordian Knots,</hi> as if they had never read <hi>the Solutions</hi> of the Vindicator. But I will conclude with him, with only obſerving ſomething to what he has, with his uſual Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Sagacity, objected to the Hopes of Salvation in the Unitarian way.</p>
               <p>The Note-maker had ſaid, that, <q>In theſe Points which have been always controverted in the Churches of God, 'tis not neceſſary to Salvation, that a Man happen to be of the right Perſwaſion; 'tis ſufficient if he uſe <hi>reaſonable Diligence</hi> to be informed; if after that he miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes, he is in <hi>no fault at all,</hi> his Error is <hi>pure Ignorance,</hi> not a culpable Ignorance; for how can it be culpable not to know that, of which a Man is ignorant <hi>after a diligent and impartial Inquiry?</hi>
                  </q> To this the Vindicator anſwers in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pages, but all <hi>the Argument</hi> of his Anſwer is in theſe words,
<q>Then how comes an Atheiſt, a Turk, or a Jew to be in any fault? Does the Note-maker think that no Atheiſt, Turk, or Jew ever uſed <hi>reaſonable Diligence?</hi> And why ſhould not their reaſonable Diligence ſerve their turns, as well as the reaſonable Diligence of <hi>Socinians,</hi> and other Hereticks?—And does not the Reaſon he gives, extend <hi>to the whole Chriſtian Religion,</hi> as well as to thoſe Points that (he ſays) have been always controverted in the Churches of God?</q>
               </p>
               <p>To this Complement of the Vindicator, I anſwer. 1. I do not think Atheiſm ever was <hi>the abiding</hi> Sentiment of any Man, who took time to conſider; and I deny that any Atheiſt ever uſed <hi>reaſonable,</hi> or but tolerable <hi>Diligence to be informed.</hi> 2. As to Jews and Turks, who believe and worſhip the one true God, and him only; perhaps they are in a nearer Proximity to Salvation than ſuch, as againſt ſufficient Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of a right Information, and for Worldly Intereſts have apoſtatized from the Chriſtian Faith, to the Athanaſian. 3. Thoſe that deny <hi>the whole Chriſtian Religion,</hi> after having known it and the Reaſons of it, the Note<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker is aſſured whatever <hi>Diligence</hi> they may have uſed, they have not made (as the Notes expreſly require) an <hi>Impartial Inquiry.</hi> They have been <hi>byaſſed</hi> by their Prejudices, or their Luſts, <hi>againſt the whole Chriſtian Faith;</hi> as others (we ſee) are byaſſed againſt <hi>the moſt Eſſential</hi> Parts of it, the Unity of God, <hi>his Inſinite</hi> Sapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, Goodneſs, Juſtice, and Power, <hi>his real</hi> Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipreſence, the Liberty of our Wills to Good and Evil. If the Vindicator thinks otherways, let him ſpeak out, and plainly tell the World his Mind; that a Man may have uſed <hi>reaſonable Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence,</hi> and alſo made <hi>an Impartial Inquiry,</hi> and yet disbelieve <hi>the whole Chriſtian Religion.</hi> This, I hope, may be enough to Dr. <hi>Sherlock</hi> at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>As for Mr. <hi>Savage,</hi> who hath alſo written a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Brief Notes, if he had pleaſed to write after an intelligible manner, he ſeems to be a Perſon that might have deſerved a careful Anſwer: But having wrapt himſelf up in a School-Cloud, and wrote in ſuch towring Meta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſicks, as are much above ordinary or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned Capacities. I am ſenſible that, with reſpect to the Unitarian Cauſe, his Book can do neither good nor hurt. However, the Unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians thank him for his deſign to inform and inſtruct them; and they deſire him not to take it amiſs, if they alſo adviſe him, that the next time he writes for the Information of the <hi>Illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate</hi> and <hi>Vulgar,</hi> he would write more intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibly. For, <hi>Learning's Light, when held too high, goes out.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
